Room, are we on the record?
OK,
this hearing of the New Mexico Department
of Health will now come to order.
I would like to welcome you to the public
hearing on the proposed new Rule 7.
35 Point 2 NMAC,
the New Mexico Psilocybin Program.
My name is Craig Erickson and I've been
appointed by the Department of Health
Cabinet Secretary Gina de Blasi to act as
the hearing officer in this matter and I
will be presiding over the hearing today.
Deputy General Counsel Chris Woodward
will be advising the Department in this
proceeding and Dominic Zerlow,
Director of the Center for Medical
Cannabis and Psilocybin,
will provide a a brief summary of what is
happening in the proposed new rule and
address topics raised in the written
public comments that have been received
by the Department so far.
Pursuant to this to notice,
this matter is being heard this 24th day
of April 2026 via a live web-based video
conference and via telephone.
Also pursuant to notice,
the public has been given the opportunity
to comment on the proposed rule via the
live base web video conference and
telephonically.
And if you're here in person, in person,
the opportunity to also given the public
given to the public to submit written
comments via e-mail messages through the
close of Business Today.
This is a recorded perceiving proceeding
and the time is approximately 9 O 2:00 AM.
This proceeding is being held in
accordance with NMSA 1978,
Section 9-7-60 of the Department of
Health Act and and NMSA 1978, 262-D7,
which requires that the Department
promulgate requirements,
restrictions and limitations on the
psilocybin program,
as well as necessary training,
safety protocols,
best practices and requirements for data
collection.
We'll proceed in the following manner.
Dr.
Zulu will give a brief introduction
regarding the rule as I described.
Mr.
Woodward will then move to enter the
exhibits into the record,
which will include the public comments
that are submitted by you all.
And then we'll take comments from each
person who would like to make public
comments today.
And because of the number of people we
anticipate may want to comment that we're
limiting your time to 5 minutes,
I'll remind those giving comments today
that this hearing is being recorded.
And then before you speak,
please stay for the record,
your full name and who you represent if
you're here on behalf of some entity,
and you should come forward to speak at
the mic.
The Department is not bound by the formal
rules of evidence during these
proceedings.
However,
I may and my discretion exclude evidence
that is incompetent, irrelevant,
immaterial or unduly repetitious.
I may also take to notice of judicially
cognizable technical or scientific facts
within the department,
specialized knowledge.
And I think with that,
we can move to the introduction to the
rule from Doctor Gerol.
Thank you and good morning, everybody.
Thank you for being here and being
present.
So the rule essentially covers the
initiation and the application process
for cultivators for medical psilocybin,
transport of medical psilocybin and the
rules for applications and the starting
of psilocybin testing laboratories.
That rule has been published on the
department website and also on the
Sunshine portal.
We did yesterday also post on the
Sunshine Portal a list of anticipated
revisions and for those who are here in
person,
we do have that list also in the back of
the room.
In brief,
those anticipated revisions are for
Section 7.35 dot 27-A1.
Revise the definition of actual control
as follows.
Actual control means the ability to
control the policies, management,
or personnel of a permittee.
B Control strategic priorities,
capital allocations,
acquisitions and divestments of a
permittee or C Control a majority of
voting rights of a permittee and on the
written document and also on the document
on the Sunshine portal.
There is explanation with regard to these
in case just as a a general,
these are based upon comments that had
already been submitted to the department.
The second change is 7.35 two dot 2.7 A2.
Revise the definition of administration
session as follows Two administration
session means the session in which
psilocybin is administered.
The third change 7.35 dot 2.7 I 2.
Revise the definition of inoculate as
follows 2.
Inoculate means the process of
introducing psilocybin spores or mycelium
into growth medium.
4 7.35 dot 2.
8 Revised application Submittal
requirements concerning rental properties
as follows.
A General requirements.
An applicant for a producer or laboratory
permit shall provide to the department
and shall maintain the following record.
Part 9.
Proof of ownership of the facility or a
signed written statement from the owner
of the property acknowledging that the
owner understands that psilocybin
products will be produced or tested on
the premises.
Five.
Part 7.35 dot 2.9.
C Revised restrictions on transferability
of permits as follows.
See permits non transferable.
A permit shall not be transferred by sale,
assignment, or otherwise,
except as approved by the department upon
the death of a sole proprietor.
The 6th item 7.35.2.
19 E Table 1 revised total yeast and
molds action level from 20 CFU to 1000
CFU.
And as a note,
that is the revision based on the
recommended limit set by American Herbal
Products Association for yeast and molds
in powdered dried food products.
7.35.2.
19 F Specify that water content shall be
less than 10% in order to pass water
content testing.
The 8th item is 7.35 dot.
2.
26 B Specify that a courtesy copy of a
Notice of Immediate Suspension or Notice
of Proposed Disciplinary Action will be
transmitted to the Permittee via e-mail
in addition to service via certified U.S.
Postal mail and item 97.35.2.19 Table 4.
Modify certain pesticide testing action
levels as follows.
And pardon me for my pronunciation,
I do not normally pronounce names of
pesticides.
So Abimectin changing to 0.15,
Bifenthrin changing to 0.
1 and Metrophenone had a misspelling,
a typo in the name and changing to 0.5.
And those revisions are to correct
typographic errors and to more closely
reflect some of the relevant standards
currently.
And with that,
I turn it back to the hearing officer.
Thank you.
At this time, Mr.
Woodward will introduce a move to place
into evidence the exhibits.
Can you hear me?
OK,
so I'm going to go down the list of
exhibits for this hearing and these are
posted online.
We don't yet have these exhibits on the
DoH rules web page,
but if you go to the Sunshine Portal
rules hearing page,
if you just Google the expression NM
Sunshine Portal rule hearings and choose
the first option,
the exhibits are posted there under
Department of Health and it's under 7.
35 point 2 and you'll see it in the list
of documents at the end there.
So we have a total of 9 exhibits to
introduce.
The first one is a letter from the New
Mexico State Records Center and Archives.
So because we were creating a new a new
chapter,
we had to request approval from the State
Records Center and Archives for that.
So Exhibit 1 is just the approval dated
February 24th of this year,
the approval by state records for the
creation of a new chapter.
So this is going to be under Title 7,
which is health, and then Chapter 35,
Medical use of psilocybin.
Exhibit 2 is the proposed new rule and
that starts on Page 3 of the PDF,
Exhibit 40.
Exhibit Exhibit 2 is the proposed rule.
Exhibit 3 is the Notice of Public Hearing
that starts on page 22 of the PDF
document.
That's the notice of hearing for today's
hearing with a description of the
proposed rule and how public comments can
be submitted.
Exhibit 4 is an affidavit of publication
from the Albuquerque Journal.
And so this is an affidavit from the
Journal just attesting to the publication
of the notice of hearing that it was
published on March 24th in the
classifieds of the Albuquerque Journal.
Exhibit 5 is let me find it.
Exhibit 5 is an affidavit of publication
for the New Mexico Register that begins
and on page 26 of the PDF and continues.
So this is just a an affidavit attesting
that the notice appearing was duly
published in the New Mexico Register by
State Records Center and Archives on that
same date.
Well, it was.
Looks like it was published.
Yeah,
it was on the same date as the
Albuquerque Journal publication.
Exhibit 6 is the letter appointing the
hearing officer in this matter,
Craig Erickson.
This is dated March 5th,
and it's signed by the Cabinet Secretary,
Gina Deblasi.
That's on page 28 of the PDF.
Exhibit 7 is an affidavit of notice to
the public.
So this is an affidavit signed by Jacob
Clark attesting to the various things
that the Department of Health has done to
comply with the notice requirements of
the State Rules Act.
And that is on page 29 of the PDF.
Page 30 is the on page 30 of the PDF is
Exhibit A.
This is the list of anticipated revisions
to 7.35,
point 2 that Mister Zerlow was referring
to.
And there are copies available up at the
front if you're interested.
Those again are not exhaustive changes,
but they're just changes of the
department knew as of this point that it
was anticipating making.
But we will be continuing to receive
public comment through the end of today's
hearing.
And Exhibit 9 consists of the public
comments themselves.
So that begins on page 33 of the PDF.
And as I say,
we'll we'll continue receiving those and
include those in the exhibit.
And so with all of that being said,
I would ask if the hearing officer admit
exhibits one through 9 into the record of
today's receiving,
the exhibits one through 9 will be
admitted into the record.
And as indicated,
if there are any additional written
comments that come in today before 5:00,
they will be added to the record as well.
At this time,
I think we can open the proceeding to
comments from the public.
And I guess I'd like to ask Mr.
Woodward to comment on how that will will
work in terms of offering public comments.
OK, So we're well Doctor Zirly,
would you like to speak to that?
Essentially each individual and if you're
here in person, you would have signed in,
in the sign in sheet in the back.
If you did not sign in to do public
comment, would like to do so.
You can still request that.
We'll have people will call them up by
name and we will just need to have people
come up to the podium.
If you have mobility issues,
one of our staff will bring the
microphone to you.
So please just indicate that to us and
we're happy to help and accommodate for
those individuals who are online.
Once we have completed going through the
public comment for those who are here in
person,
then we will open it online for those
individuals to provide comment as well.
And to do so,
we just simply need to have you raise
your hand within teams and then we will
unmute you at that time.
Once we call your name,
you can then unmute yourself on your end
and then provide the comment.
So with that we can proceed, OK.
And the first individual is Denali Wilson,
5 minutes, right?
I'm going to try and have a stopwatch too
for myself.
And, and just to let you know,
we do have a time keeper on the side of
the flash card.
Awesome.
So, OK,
so if you could say your full name for
the record, please,
and if you're representing someone,
if you could indicate that as well.
And be sure to talk as well as you can
into the microphone somewhere.
You're recording.
The post gets recorded.
Well, thank you all.
I'm grateful to be here this morning.
My name is Denali Wilson.
I am the state director of strategic
support for the Healing Advocacy Fund,
which is a nonprofit that supports state
regulated access to psychedelic healing
with a focus on access and equity within
the systems.
So I'm really grateful to have the
opportunity to participate in rulemaking
and want to move quickly through some
things.
I'm trying to be as responsive as I can
to the anticipated revisions.
So I want to start by talking about
predatory financing and disguised control,
which is an area where we provided
feedback to the department.
And I'm really grateful for the
department prioritizing this and,
and willing being willing to consider
recommendations that we've made to
improve these protections.
You know, as a state,
we have a really long history of economic
exploitation and extraction.
And I think we all have a shared interest
in making sure that this not become
another place where outside money and
interest come in and take advantage of
our people and our resources.
I want to say that the amendments don't
fully address this problem.
And even with the changes to actual
control,
the regulations continue to still to
broadly restrict ownership arrangements
and risk unintentionally prohibiting
things that are beneficial and legitimate
non predatory financing arrangements,
while at the same time not protecting
enough to prohibit more sophisticated
arrangements of disguised control or
other deceitful and predatory practices.
Under the current draft regulations and
under these proposed amendments,
it is still unclear whether a party could,
and if so,
how they can invest in a permittee
without taking responsibility for the
compliance and actions of the permittee.
And that given the lack of traditional
investment vehicles that are available in
this space, right,
involving a Schedule 1 substance,
we don't have traditional financing and
banks that lack of clarity would lock
away needed capital like even friends and
family investments out of local
operations.
We hope that there's an opportunity to
continue to iterate on and improve these
critical and foundational protections
further in the rule making process.
Really we believe that the solution is
not to restrict investment broadly,
but to instead distinguish clearly
between those who are exercising actual
control over a permitted business and
those who are hold a more passive
interest.
And so we've offered some suggestions
that reframe around around these
distinctions in order to strengthen
protections for permittees in the program
from bad actors while preserving access
to what is very limited capital in the
field.
I want to move to another Equity issue
that we talked a lot about in
subcommittee and also was a part of our
written feedback.
And this is the landlord attestation
piece.
I want to start by acknowledging that New
Mexico is the first state to allow for
non property owners to operate within the
cannabis industry.
And that was a tremendous step in equity
and access in the cannabis space and
changed dramatically the national
landscape.
And I'm really proud to live in a state
that that modelled that.
We also know that it created very new
challenges,
and I'm grateful that the department has
taken an interest in making sure that
we're protecting tenants.
I think the amendment in this provision
still needs work.
Landlords,
even those who are supportive of their
tenants in the program,
are unlikely to provide written approval
to engage in conduct that remains
federally illegal on the premises and any
attestation would amount to written proof
in a legally binding document of aiding
and abetting the manufacturing of a
Schedule 1 substance as as amended.
There still is reference to a landlord
acknowledgement of that that activity and
I think that's going to be a major
barrier.
We think really there does still need to
be a landlord,
a lease option and the the department can
specify that the lease must be protective
of the tenants rights to participate.
That could include, you know,
model language of a,
an anti illegality clause that requires
the landlord not to act on or the
landlord acknowledges that they won't act
on their right to to end the contract and
the lease.
I will end there and maybe come back if
there's time.
The next individual we have on the list
is actually listed as a maybe Michael
Williams.
No.
OK.
Thank you.
Thank you, Mr.
Williams.
The next individual is Kate Hawk.
Good morning, Miss Hawk.
Good morning.
I'm Kate Hawk.
Are you here on your own behalf?
I am here on my own.
OK.
Thank you.
Yeah.
I just had a question that that has come
up about after all of the, you know,
the things that are spelled out,
there's just a comment about our in the
that says something about selling to
practitioners.
And we were wondering as practitioners,
the medical prescribers,
is it the people who are referred to as
guides?
You know, that was just a question.
So I just wanted,
I don't know if that's within the scope
of what we're talking about today,
but that was just a question that came up
that we are wanting clarification on.
Would you like to speak to that?
Just as a note,
the items as far as the definitions with
regard to practitioners,
guides and with regard to treatment are
not a part of this rule.
They are there as placeholders at this
time and as the additional rule hearings
where some of those definitions are
defined,
that will be clarified at that time.
OK, thank you.
Thank you.
And the next individual who has requested
to speak is Hanifa Washington.
I'm going to Fargo,
but it's not like my time.
OK.
And for those who may not have been able
to hear,
Miss Washington said that she was going
to forgo but would be happy to yield it
to Miss Denali Wilson.
Is that all right with the department?
Absolutely.
Thank you.
And just while Miss Wilson comes up to
the mic, the next individual,
just so you're prepared,
will be James Ferrera.
Hi again again Denali Wilson with the
Healing Advocacy Fund and thank you honey
for free yielding some time.
I don't think I need the full 5 minutes
to complete this thought on,
on the landlord attestation issue,
really any attestation that requires I,
I understand and appreciate that the
amendment moves right.
There's,
there's now not a need for a written
approval from the owner,
but acknowledgement.
I think still we're really close to a
line of aiding and abetting, right?
We're talking about federally illegal
activity and something that landlords are
are really going to be unwilling to write
and to, to engage in writing.
And,
and right as as we're thinking about
centering equity and access in all
aspects of our of this industry and
really making sure that small growers are
able to participate.
So if you are owning the property where,
where they'd like to grow and I,
I'd really like us to see,
like to see us spend some more time
making sure we get this right.
So my recommendation is twofold.
One,
that the acknowledgement that if there is
an attestation piece that that's
specifically not reference a Schedule 1
substance, the landlords will will not,
you know,
whether it's acknowledgement or approval
or I,
I think anything that requires a landlord
to specifically endorse in some way the
growing of a schedule 1 substance on
their property is going to be ill advised.
And, and secondly,
I think it would be most beneficial to
have a lease option for landlords and
tenants who would prefer to keep all
protective legal agreements within the
actual lease.
And the department could and the
department could easily write model lease
agreement which would be happy to,
to offer and provide as,
as an example and say, you know,
this level of protection or greater.
So those are,
those are my recommendations in general,
right.
Any,
any access issues that we create at this
at this early juncture in the department
are,
are going to have a foundational impact
on the the viability and the longevity
and the the actual equity that people
experience within the program.
As a another note,
just in general on compliance and cost,
it may be helpful for the department to
consider a cost analysis for some of the
testing requirements that it's outlined
as as well as,
as well as the creation of a compliance
guide, right?
In addition to the rules that are
promulgated now,
we want people to comply and the
department does not want to enforce
actions against cultivators.
I I presume we'd rather people comply.
So I'd like to recommend that in addition
to the rules promulgated,
maybe addressing resources that provide a
compliance guide for people in these
spaces.
That's all.
Thank you again, Hanifa.
Thank you.
And James Ferreira.
Morning, everyone.
James Ferreira from Ignite Synergy.
And so I wanted to just take a few
moments to thank, you know,
the Department of Health and Dominic
especially for putting together this.
Everybody has served in all the
committees.
The work has been incredible.
The speed is unprecedented,
I think for state agencies moving on such
a such a topic for just a moment,
you probably shouldn't be turning your
head away.
Oh, sorry, sorry.
It's not not receiving for everybody.
One of the things that we've looked at is
Ignites Energy,
the company that is an outcomes focused
software force specifically built for
psychedelics.
We know that data collection is going to
be an important piece of this,
being able to actually say what our
outcomes are.
And we're forming a medical Advisory
Board that we would like to just let
people know.
You can contact us and let us know you'd
like to be on the board so we can make
some really smart decisions about data
and data management.
So when we do start collecting data,
it will, you know,
it will actually mean something.
This is the first time humans have ever
collected this kind of data,
and we think it's really important.
Thank you.
And the next individual is Gregory Evans.
Mr.
Evans.
And while Mr.
Evans comes on down to the mic,
the next individual after this will be
James Brown.
Nobody wants to go to represent.
If you represent anyone,
please let us know.
My name is Gregory Evans.
I am an independent mycologist.
I do not have any formal affiliations.
Thank you.
Nobody wants to follow James Brown.
OK, bear with me.
I have submitted as of 844 this morning a
formal public comment.
I will try to summarize that and hit the
high points.
First off, I want to thank the department,
all of the committee members,
everybody who's been involved for support
and pushing this thing forward the way
that we have.
I do not like public speaking.
I am here trying to do my best.
So there's a couple things that I wanted
to cover.
Pardon me.
The department adopted the 10% water
content in the rule,
and that is the correct direction.
The water content measures total moisture.
It does not measure whether anything can
actually grow in the product.
That would be water activity.
I have a specific recommendation to
include water activity at .6.
If we do this that aligns with the 10% in
the control window.
If we are at .6 AW nothing.
Most of the testing panel for microbials
will not be able to grow.
And if we maintain cadence testing with
water content and water availability,
we will be able to reduce the cost to all
parties with like a $25 sample cost.
Like, there's a lot more impact on that,
but we can reduce the microbial testing
with by utilizing that initial release
test and keeping storage within a
constraint parameter.
There were a number of items in the
traceability section that required some
refinement.
There were areas where cultivation batch
wasn't included in the lot hierarchy and
other sections so that lot hierarchy
definitions are all mapped out in the
recommendation.
Among the definitions I have 8 amendments
on a high level.
Please let me know when I'm out of time.
So if you notice there's he has a green
card means you're still within your time.
Thank you friend.
You corrected a typo in inoculate,
but I would like to move forward.
Recommending inoculate means the process
of introducing spores, mycelium,
or spawn into growth medium.
Inoculate is a verb and needs to be
treated as such.
I have a detailed recommendation on
psilocybin.
I'll let that stand.
As is the difference between cultivation
and manufacture regularly through the
ruling they have overlapping scope.
Noted.
I have a detailed in my item number three.
I've detailed how to clean that mapping
and define the definition between the
moment of cultivation and the moment of
manufacture relating to back to relating
to traceability.
In that section there is another
definition of where unique IDs change
from state change to state change.
Basically we were missing batch and then
when we become a harvest lot the
definition of that was ambiguous.
So I've clarified that mycelium
definition.
Mycelium means the vegetative body of a
fungus composed of a network of
filamentous structure called hyphy.
Is that hard?
That's your time.
Thank you.
And Mr.
James Brown.
Good morning.
Morning, Sir, and everyone.
My name is James Brown and I represent 5°
N Healing Foundation.
Oh, sorry,
I can raise this a little bit actually,
if you just want to take it out is that
might be easier.
Is that, is that OK?
I could probably do that.
5° N Healing Foundation, is that there?
It's a nonprofit here in New Mexico that
focuses with veterans, first responders,
PTSD, and other things.
We're hoping to be a,
a center that offers administration
sessions and for whatever that definition
or terminology would be.
I'm trained through Oregon currently in a
a psilocybin focused 12 week program that
I think that would very benefit New
Mexico to look at as we get through that
program.
And again,
I just want to thank everybody here and
the program itself and Chris give him
some shout out for his time and effort,
you know,
to come up with this stuff and and the
chair of this again,
public speaking stuff.
So especially in the setting.
So again,
I'm here to to really focus on some of my
comments that I put in and and really
just the the the 7.35 point 2.9,
the general permente requirements.
And you know,
just to go back on that focus and you
know, with New Mexico being such a rural,
such an amazing and beautiful state,
but we're very rural and we really got to
think about that when we think about
these rules.
It's just the thought and,
and use a filter of that.
And,
and with this medicine that we're going
to be providing these people the
opportunity to experience something that
maybe they've had experience with before,
maybe they haven't.
And,
and these rules are a great start and I
think we've done a great job as a group.
And thank you again for for doing this
today to allow us to come in front of you
and, and present our comments to you.
And so my focus would be on just that,
that whole dual ownership.
You know, my whole thing today is that,
you know,
to allow us to the wording or I really
think we just focus on not saying and
restricting so much of of that language
of saying you cannot own both.
But maybe or because as a permenti,
I think it's important to be able to to
have a Sinner,
but also maybe have a grill, right.
As mycologist,
you're going to have these groups of
people and so you can have this great
network that these people can tap into.
And so within your own group,
within your own business,
I've owned quite a few businesses.
And within that,
you need opportunity to grow your
business because you might have Fiber 5
people within your network,
like in a nonprofit,
and those people might be specialists in
their groups.
And within that they might have a grower,
A mycologist.
That's amazing.
And so you need that opportunity.
And so that would be the permenti there.
But also I might have a provider who's a
doctor,
but within that same group in that
nonprofit,
I want to be able to have a center.
And so I just want to make sure that
languaging in that dual ownership allows
us to have that type of opportunity in
New Mexico and also give other New
Mexicans opportunities.
Being so rural again, Roswell, Farmington,
little states, you know,
there were only so big, right?
And so there's only going to be so many
providers, so many facilitators,
so many centers.
And so think about that.
And so I just really want to open up that
languaging to maybe the words of of it
being able to have the opportunity to
have both,
but not the laboratory and the grow,
but just that thought.
So thank you so much today.
I do appreciate you.
Thank you.
At this time we have everybody who had
signed up to speak on the sign in sheet.
We have gone through there.
So if we can turn to the computer,
if there's anyone who is on the virtual
setting who would like to speak,
if you would please raise your hand now
and we will go in that order and we'll
give just a moment or so for individuals
to raise their hand.
And just as a reminder to raise your hand,
just it within Teams.
It is if you're on a computer,
it is towards the top of the screen,
the little hand icon,
just simply click on it.
If you're on a phone,
it is usually in one of the lower corners
and just click on that item.
So if they call me in Starfire and if you
are on a phone and not on a computer and
just doing by audio,
then it would be *5 to raise your hand.
I can.
And we're just giving individuals a
minute or so to be able to raise their
hand.
And I believe we have one individual at
this time.
All right, first up, we have John,
Dennis and John.
What's John's last name?
Dennis.
All right, John, I've enabled your mic.
You can speak when you're ready.
OK.
Thank you to Doctor Zerlow and to the
department for giving us an opportunity
to comment on these rules.
It's my great honor and privilege to
speak to you today on behalf of the
Psychedelic Bar Association and it's New
Mexico Working Group.
Our working group includes 9 lawyers and
legal professionals from across New
Mexico and the United States who are
volunteering their time to engage with
and to provide input on New Mexico's
rulemaking.
In order to help ensure that this program
is the best that it can be,
we submitted a written comments and today
I'm speaking just to two of the points
raised in those comments.
The first comment I'd like to kind of
highlight is our input on taxation under
the Section 2 Ade of the Internal Revenue
Code.
If the goal of the program is to keep
cost to as low as they can be to Section
2 Ade liability should be really
minimized to the extent possible.
For folks who aren't familiar with
Section 2 AE it,
it's a it's a tax rule that requires that
any organization or individual who is
trafficking in a Schedule one or Schedule
2 substance must pay taxes and is not
able to deduct the standard deductions
and expenses that they incur in the cost
of operating their business.
So with respect to how to minimize that
tax liability in the state of Oregon in
its psilocybin program,
the common practice is for operators to
bifurcate their liability so that those
asked portions of their operations that
are plant touching or or mushroom
touching that would be engaged in
trafficking activities are maintained
separately from the other aspects of the
operations that are not plant touching.
So that all of that liability can be sort
of isolated and and contained within as
small a portion of the operations as
possible.
This kind of structuring that is pretty
common.
Not everybody structures their
organizations that way,
but but many do and it does substantially
reduce the amount of tax liability that
those organizations have.
But there is an opportunity to go further
than that and that would be through
allowing the direct manufacturer to
consumer or patient sales.
We understand that there is a very
legitimate state interest in avoiding
diversion and similar types of behaviors.
And so we understand there's a series of
protections and guardrails that should go
around this.
But if the facilitator or guide is not
actually delivering the substances to
clients or patients,
that would enable those multiple hours,
potentially as many as 10 hours per
administration session to not be taxed at
this significantly higher level.
So if the state were to allow some kind
of abbreviated touch point with the the
actual transfer of psilocybin to the
patient directly,
it could provide an opportunity to save
costs, reduce the tax burden.
That is a really significant aspect of
this.
It's more significant for those who are
familiar with the way that 280 E plays
out in the cannabis space.
With cannabis, it's just retail,
so you're not really having to pay for
hours of support and supervision and
facilitation and that sort of thing.
So the impact that 280 E has on a
regulated services model such as New
Mexico's is significantly more than it is
even in the cannabis space.
So allowing these direct sales or or some,
you know,
interim person who isn't otherwise
providing like hours of services to the
patient is a is a pretty good opportunity
to keep cost low and and keep it as
affordable as possible under all the
circumstances.
The second point I wanted to speak to
briefly is around you have 30 seconds.
OK, thank you.
The written comments speak about the the
accidental, potentially the inadvertent,
authorization of religious use in the
state of New Mexico by the passage of
this medical Psilocybin Act.
We cite the three cases in our written
materials that stand for the proposition
that if the state of New Mexico or any
state is authorizing legal psilocybin
access for any reason,
it then under current US Supreme Court
precedent must also authorize religious
use of that substance.
So the ask here is that you not disparage
religious use cases and that, you know,
to the extent that this could result in
potential harms that can come from
community use in unregulated or
unsupervised setting,
the state may wish to take action to
ensure that there are safeguards and that
there's some kind of support.
OK.
Thank you.
All right.
I'm not seeing any other hands up online.
Just as a reminder that should be if
you're on Teams on the desktop up with a
hand that says Ray's icon in the top bar.
And if you are dialed in via phone,
it would be a *5 if you are not on the
Teams app.
All right,
I am not seeing any hands raised at this
time.
That will conclude the public comments
for during today I'll tell you a little
bit about the process from here on out.
I'm obligated to write a a report that
summarizes the written comments and
summarize the public comments are given
here today.
Do the Secretary and then make a
recommendation to her regarding whatever
I think in response to the materials that
have been presented and that will be
forthcoming after this hearing,
I think is there any anything else we
need to address?
I think that's it.
OK Well,
thank you all for participating today.
And at that point,
we'll conclude the hearing and go off the
record.
Thank you everybody and thank you
everyone for.